<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article article-type="news" dtd-version="2.3" xml:lang="EN" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><front>
<journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">SCIENCE</journal-id><journal-title>Science</journal-title><abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="pubmed">Science</abbrev-journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0036-8075</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1095-9203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>American Association for the Advancement of Science</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="article-type"><subject>News of the Week</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>News of the Week</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="legacy-article-type"><subject>n-week</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="field"><subject>PHYSICS</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="overline"><subject>Fusion</subject></subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Budget Red Tape in Europe Brings New Delay to ITER</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Clery</surname><given-names>Daniel</given-names></name></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<day>19</day>
<month>03</month>
<year>2010</year>
</pub-date><volume>327</volume><issue>5972</issue><fpage>1434</fpage><lpage>1434</lpage><permissions>
<copyright-statement>Copyright &#x00A9; 2010, American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2010</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract abstract-type="teaser"><p>The projected start of the ITER fusion reactor in France looks set to slip by another 10 months. The new completion date is now November 2019.</p></abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="web-summary"><p>The projected start of the ITER fusion reactor in France looks set to slip by another 10 months. Although the new completion date of November 2019 for construction may seem like a minor schedule alteration for the multibillion-dollar research reactor, it is the tip of a large iceberg of negotiations over management structures, design changes, cost increases, and risk mitigation that has gripped the project for the past 2 years.</p></abstract>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>The projected start of the ITER fusion reactor in France looks set to slip by another 10 months. Although the new completion date of November 2019 for construction may seem like a minor schedule alteration for the multibillion-dollar research reactor, it is the tip of a large iceberg of negotiations over management structures, design changes, cost increases, and risk mitigation that has gripped the project for the past 2 years (<italic>Science</italic>, 13 November 2009, p. <related-article related-article-type="in-this-publication" vol="326" page="932" issue="5955">932</related-article>).</p>
<p>The latest proposed delay was revealed last week by William Brinkman, director of the U.S. Department of Energy&apos;s Office of Science, at a meeting of scientific advisers to the government&apos;s fusion research program. <italic>Science</italic> has learned that it stems in part from budgetary problems in approving contracts by the European Union. &#x201C;Europe turned out [to be] a weak link. &#x2026; [It] must fulfill its commitments,&#x201D; Russian researcher Yevgeny Velikhov, who chairs the ITER Council, told Russian Prime Minister Vladimir Putin in February, according to an official transcript of the meeting. Still, fusion researchers who spoke with <italic>Science</italic> say they are confident that this and other hurdles can be worked out in time for a meeting of the ITER Council in June, removing perhaps the final obstacles to starting ITER construction.</p>
<p>ITER aims to harness fusion&#x2014;the process that powers the sun and stars&#x2014;to produce usable amounts of energy. Its site, in Cadarache, France, has been ready for about a year, and components are being built by all of the ITER partners&#x2014;China, the European Union, India, Japan, South Korea, Russia, and the United States. But the partners still have not agreed to ITER&apos;s detailed design, schedule, and joint costs, together known as the project baseline.</p>
<p>Most of the reactor components are manufactured by each partner&apos;s home industry and delivered to Cadarache as contributions in-kind. The manufacturing jobs were divvied up in an agreement drafted in 2005&#x2013;06, but most partners found out later that they had underestimated the cost of what they had agreed to. The United States, which had estimated a $1 billion bill, is now looking at somewhere between $1.4 billion and $2.2 billion. The European Union, as host, will build 45% of the reactor, and so its cost increases are the largest.</p>
<p>In June 2008, the ITER Council pushed back the date for the reactor&apos;s first plasma by 2 years, to 2018. Last November, the European Union requested further delays, but the other partners wanted to push ahead. Part of the problem lies in the European Union&apos;s desire to build prototypes of two key elements&#x2014;its parts of the vacuum vessel that surrounds the plasma, and half of the toroidal field coils that hold the plasma in place&#x2014;before making the final items. A 2018 start-up would require the European Union to begin building the manufacturing facility before the prototypes were finished and tested, running the risk of requiring expensive changes to a partly built facility.</p>
<p>E.U. officials have insisted that they asked for more time to mitigate such risks. But fusion researchers who spoke with <italic>Science</italic> on the condition of anonymity say there is another reason. According to E.U. financial rules, officials cannot sign a deal with a contractor unless funding for the whole contract is available. Yet E.U. nuclear research funding is approved in 4-year chunks, and the current budget, which runs through 2011, doesn&apos;t cover the now-inflated costs. &#x201C;The E.U. cannot promise money it doesn&apos;t have,&#x201D; says one researcher.</p>
<p>Some contracts for ITER&apos;s components may be worth hundreds of millions of euros over 7 or 8 years, and the European Union simply doesn&apos;t have enough money in its current coffer. Insiders say there was talk of a loan from the European Investment Bank&#x2014;an E.U. institution&#x2014;to guarantee the contracts, but some E.U. member states rejected that idea. The European Union would not confirm any budgetary problems, saying that the current schedule &#x201C;would have entailed extraordinary measures to accelerate activities in the building phase &#x2026; and would increase unnecessarily risk and associated costs.&#x201D;</p>
<fig id="F1" position="float">
<caption>
<title>Assembly required.</title>
<p>Europe wants to make prototypes of its parts for the ITER reactor (<italic>above</italic>).</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="327_1434_F1"/>
<attrib>CREDIT: &#x00A9; ITER ORGANIZATION</attrib>
</fig>
<p>The E.U.&apos;s proposal to last November&apos;s ITER Council meeting was for a 2020 start, but the other partners refused. Last month in Paris, delegates provisionally compromised on November 2019. Velikhov&apos;s conversation with Putin is one of several signs that ITER partners are exasperated by the delays. The 2011 budget request to Congress by President Barack Obama would cut ITER spending next year by $55 million, to $80 million. The lower figure is &#x201C;a reflection of the pace of ITER construction as of the end of 2009,&#x201D; U.S. Energy Secretary Steven Chu told a Senate spending panel last month.</p>
<p>The ITER organization is now adjusting the baseline document to the new schedule for review by two advisory panels before seeking final approval by the ITER Council in June. Researchers remain hopeful that agreement on the baseline will remove the logjam slowing ITER construction. &#x201C;There&apos;s a sense that ITER is reaching a turning point, moving in a positive direction,&#x201D; says Steward Prager, director of the Princeton Plasma Physics Laboratory. Positive, yes; but it&apos;s not moving there fast enough for some.</p>
</body>
</article>
