<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article article-type="other" dtd-version="2.3" xml:lang="EN" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">SCIENCE</journal-id>
<journal-title>Science</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="pubmed">Science</abbrev-journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0036-8075</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1095-9203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>American Association for the Advancement of Science</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1185164</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1185164</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="article-type"><subject>Policy Forum</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Policy Forum</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="legacy-article-type"><subject>p-forum</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="overline"><subject>Ecology</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="field"><subject>SCI POLICY</subject></subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>China, India, and the Environment</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bawa</surname><given-names>Kamaljit S.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Koh</surname><given-names>Lian Pin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">4</xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Tien Ming</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5">5</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff6">6</xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Jianguo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff7">7</xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ramakrishnan</surname><given-names>P. S.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff8">8</xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Douglas W.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff9">9</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff10">10</xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Ya-ping</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff9">9</xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Raven</surname><given-names>Peter H.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff11">11</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref></contrib>
<aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>University of Massachusetts, Boston, MA 02125, USA.</aff>
<aff id="aff2"><label>2</label>Sustainability Science Program, Harvard University, Cambridge, MA 02138, USA.</aff>
<aff id="aff3"><label>3</label>Ashoka Trust for Research in Ecology and the Environment, Bangalore, 560024, India.</aff>
<aff id="aff4"><label>4</label>Institute of Terrestrial Ecosystems, ETH Z&#x00FC;rich, 8092 Z&#x00FC;rich, Switzerland.</aff>
<aff id="aff5"><label>5</label>University of California, San Diego, La Jolla, CA 92093, USA.</aff>
<aff id="aff6"><label>6</label>Yale University, New Haven, CT 06520, USA.</aff>
<aff id="aff7"><label>7</label>Michigan State University, East Lansing, MI 48824, USA.</aff>
<aff id="aff8"><label>8</label>Jawaharlal Nehru University, Delhi, 110067, India.</aff>
<aff id="aff9"><label>9</label>Kunming Institute of Zoology, Kunming, 650223 Yunnan, China.</aff>
<aff id="aff10"><label>10</label>University of East Anglia, Norwich NR47TJ, UK.</aff>
<aff id="aff11"><label>11</label>Missouri Botanical Garden, St. Louis, MO 63166, USA.</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="cor1"><label>*</label>Author for correspondence. E-mail: <email>peter.raven@mobot.org</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<day>19</day>
<month>03</month>
<year>2010</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>327</volume>
<issue>5972</issue>
<fpage>1457</fpage>
<lpage>1459</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Copyright &#x00A9; 2010, American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2010</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract abstract-type="teaser">
<p>Cooperation between China and India can curtail biodiversity loss, mitigate climate change, and reduce deforestation.</p>
</abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="excerpt">
<p>China and India, the emerging economic giants of the world, will play a significant, perhaps a dominant, role in shaping the environmental outcomes for our planet in the 21st century. Both countries are expected to maintain an 8 to 9% rate of economic growth over the next several years (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1"><italic>1</italic></xref>). Even when much of the world is experiencing a recession, China and India in 2009 are projected to achieve high Gross Domestic Product growth (China, 8.4%; India, 6.2%; world, &#x2212;2.2%) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1"><italic>1</italic></xref>). Development in China and India is fueled not only by the natural capital within the countries, but also increasingly by imports of raw materials, particularly from southeast Asia. Both nations import &#x223C;9 million tons of crude palm oil annually&#x2014;almost one-quarter of global production&#x2014;mostly from Malaysia and Indonesia (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2"><italic>2</italic></xref>). The degree to which China and India consume natural resources within their boundaries, and beyond, will largely determine future environmental, social, and economic outcomes. The two countries have been engaged in a border dispute that included a bitter, but brief, war in 1962. We propose that much more earnest cooperation between the world's two most populous countries will be vital for mitigating biodiversity loss, global warming, and deforestation.</p>
</abstract>
<custom-meta-wrap><custom-meta><meta-name>Editor</meta-name><meta-value>Barbara R. Jasny</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>Copyeditor</meta-name><meta-value>Barbara Ordway</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-wrap></article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>China and India, the emerging economic giants of the world, will play a significant, perhaps a dominant, role in shaping the environmental outcomes for our planet in the 21st century. Both countries are expected to maintain an 8 to 9% rate of economic growth over the next several years (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1"><italic>1</italic></xref>). Even when much of the world is experiencing a recession, China and India in 2009 are projected to achieve high Gross Domestic Product growth (China, 8.4%; India, 6.2%; world, &#x2212;2.2%) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1"><italic>1</italic></xref>). Development in China and India is fueled not only by the natural capital within the countries, but also increasingly by imports of raw materials, particularly from southeast Asia. Both nations import &#x223C;9 million tons of crude palm oil annually&#x2014;almost one-quarter of global production&#x2014;mostly from Malaysia and Indonesia (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2"><italic>2</italic></xref>). The degree to which China and India consume natural resources within their boundaries, and beyond, will largely determine future environmental, social, and economic outcomes. The two countries have been engaged in a border dispute that included a bitter, but brief, war in 1962. We propose that much more earnest cooperation between the world's two most populous countries will be vital for mitigating biodiversity loss, global warming, and deforestation.</p>
<sec>
<title>Biodiversity, Water, Climate, and Forests</title>
<p>Nowhere are these issues better exemplified than in the Himalayas, the 2400-km-long chain of mountain ranges stretching between the Indus and the Brahmaputra River valleys (see the picture, above). The unique biodiversity of this region faces multiple pressures, including those associated with the military presence of both countries along the international border (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3"><italic>3</italic></xref>). This situation is particularly damaging to fragile subalpine and alpine ecosystems, which recover slowly from disturbance. Furthermore, resources are so scarce in these cold, high-altitude areas that the armies often use rare species for fuel.</p>
<p>Both countries are already facing severe surface and groundwater shortages (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4"><italic>4</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5"><italic>5</italic></xref>). Given the increased snow and glacier melt in the Himalaya&#x2013;Hindu Kush region (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6"><italic>6</italic></xref>), the hydrology of major Asian rivers will be severely affected in the near future. The rush to harness hydroelectric power by building hundreds of dams on both sides of the earthquake-prone Himalayas will further accelerate changes in hydrology and the effects of climate change. For instance, India plans to increase hydropower projects in the Himalayas from 74 to 355 over the next 15 years, increasing the capacity from 15,208 to 126,588 MW (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7"><italic>7</italic></xref>); China is planning 750 projects in Tibet alone (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8"><italic>8</italic></xref>). Further, China may also divert water from the Tsangpo-Brahmaputra, one of the largest rivers in Asia, before it enters India (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9"><italic>9</italic></xref>). If true, dispute over political boundaries could extend to water resources.</p>
<fig id="F1" position="float">
<caption>
    <p><bold>A Himalayan landscape</bold>&#x2014;linking environmental integrity with peace and security.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="327_1457_F1"></graphic>
<attrib>CREDIT: KAMALJIT S. BAWA</attrib>
</fig>
<p>Exploitation of Himalayan resources is likely to be accelerated as energy consumption rises more rapidly in Asia than anywhere else. China and India, respectively, are already the world's top and the fifth-largest emitters of greenhouse gases. Snow melt from Himalayan glaciers constitutes a principal water resource during the summer months for at least half of the world's population (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10"><italic>10</italic></xref>). The synergistic effects of decreasing water resources, loss of biodiversity, increased pollution, and climate change may have negative social and economic consequences and, even worse, escalate conflicts within and between the two countries.</p>
<p>Beyond the Himalayas, both countries are enlarging their ecological footprint in Asia. If current trends continue to 2020 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2"><italic>2</italic></xref>), China and India may be importing 45.8 and 18.8%, respectively, of their roundwood demand, or 64% of all currently produced roundwood in Asia. These imports will contribute to deforestation-driven greenhouse gas emissions and biodiversity loss in Asia.</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>Benefits and Barriers to Cooperation</title>
<p>China and India have much to learn from each other. For instance, India's energy efficiency is higher than China's (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11"><italic>11</italic></xref>). However, China has much to offer to India in poverty reduction, health care, and large conservation programs, including the Natural Forest Conservation Program and the Grain-to-Green Program (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12"><italic>12</italic></xref>).</p>
<p>Cooperation between the two countries could help mitigate climate change, environmental damage, and biodiversity loss both regionally and globally. Both countries, but especially China, have experience with microhydropower projects. Local communities, especially in the Himalayas, have a tremendous knowledge of biodiversity, hydrology, and climate change (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13"><italic>13</italic></xref>). Sharing this knowledge could enhance the development of appropriate approaches and technologies. Both countries have recently increased forest cover (China, 157.1 million ha in 1990 to 197.3 million ha in 2005; India, 63.9 million ha to 67.7 million ha) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2"><italic>2</italic></xref>). Sharing expertise in afforestation and in the development of policy frameworks for sustainable use of forest resources with the rest of Asia could contribute to reduction in deforestation and to an Asia-wide effort to mitigate climate change through both the preservation and enhancement of forest carbon stocks. Cooperation between the two countries can also have a huge impact on trade in tiger body parts and on conservation of the last remaining and the largest population of an icon species.</p>
<p>So far, collaboration and coordination between the two countries in dealing with environmental challenges has been limited, although there have been several signed agreements since 1988 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14"><italic>14</italic></xref>). In 1993, a Sino-India collaboration agreement on the environment was signed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15"><italic>15</italic></xref>). In the past few years, there have been research collaborations on terrestrial ecosystems, atmosphere-ocean-biosphere interactions, and related modeling (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14"><italic>14</italic></xref>) but the level of overall scientific collaboration has been lower than expected (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16"><italic>16</italic></xref>). In 2009, an international symposium on biodiversity and environmental changes in the Himalayan region was held in China and was attended by Chinese and Indian scientists (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17"><italic>17</italic></xref>). More recently, India and China have signed an agreement to comonitor glaciers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18"><italic>18</italic></xref>) and to collaborate in the areas of energy, agriculture, and afforestation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19"><italic>19</italic></xref>).</p>
<p>Despite the presence of these frameworks for cooperation, major barriers to collaboration between China and India persist. Linguistic and cultural differences perhaps tend to keep Indian and Chinese academics apart even in international meetings. Unresolved border disputes also deter cooperation. Furthermore, the severity of environmental challenges, and the opportunities for and benefits of coordinated and collaborative actions remain underappreciated.</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>Steps Toward Deepening Cooperation</title>
<p>First, both countries need to overcome cultural and linguistic barriers. Although China has been actively promoting Chinese language and culture internationally in recent years, only 2 out of 523 Confucius Institutes that have been established worldwide to support local teaching of Chinese are in India (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20"><italic>20</italic></xref>). Similarly, India needs to promote Chinese studies in India and Indian studies in China.</p>
<p>Second, with sparse or no human populations, some of the disputed areas or the areas where armies have been amassed, which are alpine zones, are ideal for conversion to transboundary protected areas or peace parks, similar to the proposed K-2&#x2013;Siachen Peace Park between India and Pakistan (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21"><italic>21</italic></xref>). The creation of peace parks&#x2014;for which the United Nations Educational, Scientific, and Cultural Organization (UNESCO) could develop guidelines&#x2014;and jointly run research stations could not only protect biodiversity, provide key ecosystem services, help mitigate climate change, and foster scientific collaboration, but also promote cooperative conservation actions and peaceful resolution to the border dispute (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21"><italic>21</italic></xref>).</p>
<p>Third, 2009 marked the 15th anniversary of agreements signed between the Chinese and Indian Academies of Sciences. The academies could exercise strong leadership in highlighting environmental issues, initiating joint actions, and fostering scientific exchanges. The Indian academies are gearing up to be more active in policy-making and could accord high priority to policy-oriented initiatives. Exchange and joint supervision of graduate and postdoctoral students could build on existing programs, such as those run by the Academy of Sciences for the Developing World (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22"><italic>22</italic></xref>). The governments could also establish a joint grants program for Himalayan research, as China and India have taken preliminary steps to establish a framework for scientific cooperation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23"><italic>23</italic></xref>). The ecological societies of China, Japan, and South Korea have established formal agreements for cooperation and have held regular joint meetings. Such meetings could include India and place more emphasis on the environment.</p>
<p>Fourth, the United Nations and other organizations could create mechanisms for regional cooperation and governance of natural resources. Considering the number of heritage sites in the Himalayas, UNESCO and the U.N. Environment Programme, in particular, could be key in bringing the two countries together and facilitating such cooperation. Moreover, international foundations and nongovernmental organizations that are engaged in environmental issues on both sides of the Himalayas could develop transnational programs.</p>
<p>Fifth, the existing political and economic forums, such as the East Asia Summit and the Association of Southeast Asian Nations with China, Japan, and South Korea, which primarily foster trade, could pay more attention to the environment, which sustains most economic endeavors.</p>
<p>Finally, the United States, the European Union, and other developed countries could play pivotal roles in facilitating and encouraging multinational talks on climate change and related environmental problems that transcend political boundaries. The United States has good relations with China and India, but is engaged in separate discussions with each country over economic, energy, and environmental issues. Ultimately, as China and India begin to build more confidence and consensus from within, they will settle their differences bilaterally, particularly when environmental security starts to override concern for political boundaries.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
<title>References and Notes</title>
<ref id="R1">
<label>1</label>
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab collab-type="author">World Bank</collab>, <source>Global Economic Prospects 2010: Crisis, Finance, and Growth</source> (<publisher-name>World Bank</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>, <year>2010</year>); <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.worldbank.org/gep2010">www.worldbank.org/gep2010</ext-link>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R2">
<label>2</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab collab-type="author">FAO</collab>, <article-title>FAOSTAT Online Statistical Service</article-title> (<publisher-name>Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Rome, Italy</publisher-loc>, <year>2009</year>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R3">
<label>3</label>
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab collab-type="author">Conservation International</collab>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.biodiversityhotspots.org/xp/Hotspots/himalaya/">www.biodiversityhotspots.org/xp/Hotspots/himalaya/</ext-link>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R4">
<label>4</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Briscoe</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Malik</surname><given-names>R. P. S.</given-names></name></person-group>, <source>India's Water Economy&#x2014;Bracing for a Turbulent Future</source> (<publisher-name>Oxford Univ. Press</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>, <year>2006</year>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R5">
<label>5</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>T. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Newfarmer</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group>, <source>Clear Water, Blue Skies: China's Environment in the New Century</source> (<publisher-name>World Bank</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>, <year>1997</year>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R6">
<label>6</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>., <source>Conserv. Biol.</source> <volume>23</volume>, <fpage>520</fpage> (<year>2009</year>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R7">
<label>7</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>van Gelder</surname><given-names>J. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Scheire</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kroes</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group>, <source>New Trends in the Financing of Dams&#x2014;a Research Paper Prepared for International Rivers, BankTrack, and WWF Germany</source> (<publisher-name>Profundo</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Castricum, Netherlands</publisher-loc>, <year>2008</year>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R8">
<label>8</label>
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group>, <source>Telegraph</source>, <day>14</day> <month>October</month> <year>2008</year>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/asia/tibet/3193790/China-plans-damsacross-Tibet.html">www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/asia/tibet/3193790/China-plans-damsacross-Tibet.html</ext-link>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R9">
<label>9</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pomeranz</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group>, <source>New Left Rev.</source> <volume>58</volume>, <fpage>5</fpage> (<year>2009</year>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R10">
<label>10</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barnett</surname><given-names>T. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Adam</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lettenmaier</surname><given-names>D. P.</given-names></name></person-group>, <source>Nature</source> <volume>438</volume>, <fpage>303</fpage> (<year>2005</year>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R11">
<label>11</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Diamond</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group>, <source>Nature</source> <volume>435</volume>, <fpage>1179</fpage> (<year>2005</year>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R12">
<label>12</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ouyang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tam</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name></person-group>, <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</source> <volume>105</volume>, <fpage>9477</fpage> (<year>2008</year>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R13">
<label>13</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bawa</surname><given-names>K. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Joseph</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Setty</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group>, <source>Agric. Ecosyst. Environ.</source>
<volume>121</volume>, <fpage>287</fpage> (<year>2007</year>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R14">
<label>14</label>
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abrol</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rupal</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group>, <source>SciDev.Net</source>, <day>14</day> <month>May</month> <year>2008</year>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.scidev.net">www.scidev.net</ext-link>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R15">
<label>15</label>
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab collab-type="author">JiangSu Environmental Protection Industry Network</collab>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ep898.com">ep898.com</ext-link>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ep898.com/view1.asp?id=1039">www.ep898.com/view1.asp?id=1039</ext-link>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R16">
<label>16</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hand</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group>, <source>Nature</source> <volume>463</volume>, <fpage>282</fpage> (<year>2010</year>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R17">
<label>17</label>
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab collab-type="author">Meetings China</collab>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.meetingschina.com/z_yantaohui/130050.html">www.meetingschina.com/z_yantaohui/130050.html</ext-link>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R18">
<label>18</label>
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab collab-type="author">Huanqiu.com</collab>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://china.huanqiu.com/eyes_on_china/environment-technology/2009-08/535769.html">http://china.huanqiu.com/eyes_on_china/environment-technology/2009-08/535769.html</ext-link>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R19">
<label>19</label>
<citation citation-type="web">
<article-title>&#x201C;India, China ink pact to fight climate change together,&#x201D;</article-title>
<source>Economic Times</source>, <day>21</day> <month>October</month> <year>2009</year>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://economictimes.indiatimes.com">http://economictimes.indiatimes.com</ext-link>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R20">
<label>20</label>
<citation citation-type="web">
<article-title>&#x201C;Confucius Institutes,&#x201D;</article-title> <source>Hanban</source>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://english.hanban.org/kzxy.php">http://english.hanban.org/kzxy.php</ext-link>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R21">
<label>21</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>S. H.</given-names></name></person-group>, Ed., <source>Peace Parks: Conservation and Conflict Resolution</source> (<publisher-name>MIT Press</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Cambridge, MA</publisher-loc>, <year>2007</year>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R22">
<label>22</label>
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab collab-type="author">The Academy of Science for the Developing World</collab>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://twas.ictp.it/">https://twas.ictp.it/</ext-link>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R23">
<label>23</label>
<citation citation-type="web">
<article-title>&#x201C;The National Natural Science Foundation of China and the Indian Ministry of Science and Technology signed a Memorandum of Understanding on Cooperation,&#x201D;</article-title> <day>2</day> <month>July</month> <year>2003</year>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nsfc.gov.cn/Portal0/InfoModule_407/10532.htm">www.nsfc.gov.cn/Portal0/InfoModule_407/10532.htm</ext-link>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
<ack>
<label>24</label><p>Supported in part by NSF (K.S.B. and J.L.), National Aeronautics and Space Administration (J.L.), the Blue Moon Fund (K.S.B.), W. Jetz (T.M.L.), ETH Fellowship (L.P.K.), 973 Program (2007CB411600, Y.-p.Z.), National Natural Science Foundation of China (Y.-p.Z.), and Swiss National Science Foundation (L.P.K.). J. M. Church, G. Balachnader, and three anonymous reviewers offered constructive comments.</p>
</ack>
</back>
</article>